<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A nevv booke intituled the blasinge of bawdrie Daylie procured by Beldame B. principall broker of all iniquitie. Geuen for a Newyeares gyfte, aswell to all suche: in whose charge, the due punishment ther of is co[m]mitted: as also to all other that may reap co[m]modytie by lothyng their practises, either by readyng, or hearyng of the same. By R.C. citizen.1574</title>
            <author>R. C., fl. 1574.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843877</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843877</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8639</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17477)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8639)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 524:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A nevv booke intituled the blasinge of bawdrie Daylie procured by Beldame B. principall broker of all iniquitie. Geuen for a Newyeares gyfte, aswell to all suche: in whose charge, the due punishment ther of is co[m]mitted: as also to all other that may reap co[m]modytie by lothyng their practises, either by readyng, or hearyng of the same. By R.C. citizen.1574</title>
                  <author>R. C., fl. 1574.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the vpper end of fleetlane: at the signe of the Spreade Eagle, by Richard Jhones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1574]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Includes, with caption title: An exclamacion of the autor, against the secrete bawdes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A1) B⁴(-B4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  16th century.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Social conditions --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEVV BOOKE Intituled <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The blaſinge of Bawdrie, Daylie procured by Beldame B. Principall Broker of all iniquitie.</p>
            <p>Geuen for a Newyeares Gyfte, aſwell to all ſuche: in whoſe charge, the due puniſhment therof is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: As alſo to all other that may reap co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytie by lothyng their practiſes, either by readyng, or hearyng of the ſame. (?)</p>
            <p>By R. C. Citizen. 1574.</p>
            <p>¶To all preuie Bawdes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>YE deuylyſh Drabs, that ſet your intent,</l>
               <l>Youth to beguyle, with your yll cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell</l>
               <l>Amende betyme, leaſt that ye be ſhent,</l>
               <l>And for your labours go to the Deuyl of hell</l>
               <l>Looke on this book, which doth your fauts tel,</l>
               <l>All your bawdy reuell, &amp; your yll company,</l>
               <l>Nought at al can you ſaue, whan ye ſhal di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:2"/>
            <head>¶A dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Printer and <hi>the Authour.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>BRother I meruayle how that ye,</l>
               <l>durſt againſt Bawds make relation:</l>
               <l>Seing ye haue none auctorytie,</l>
               <l>them to rebuke with reprobation.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour</speaker>
               <l>¶Euery man by charytte is bound</l>
               <l>with words at leaſt thoſe Queanes to reproue</l>
               <l>For ſurely it doth ſo much abound:</l>
               <l>That it diſpleaſeth the Deitie aboue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶That is trueth, but yet take héede,</l>
               <l>trueth is not alway to be ſayd:</l>
               <l>For though that ye know ſuch folks indéede,</l>
               <l>yet ſclaunder to you ſhall be layd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <l>¶The more pity, for I name no body</l>
               <l>I doo it only for to admoniſh</l>
               <l>Offycers, and ſuch as haue cuſtody,</l>
               <l>Ouer all ſuch folk to puniſh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶As for that ſay what ye will,</l>
               <l>ye ſhall rather hatred attayne:</l>
               <l>Spight of your hart they wil bide ſtyll,</l>
               <l>and you ſmal thank for all your payne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:3"/>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <l>¶Foule of you ſaid, euer ſpeke the beſt,</l>
               <l>Offycers that therto bee committed:</l>
               <l>As the Bedelles and Wardmot queſt,</l>
               <l>wyll in no maner take bribes for it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶I think the ſame, but I doo maruell,</l>
               <l>to my reaſon they cannot be ſparde:</l>
               <l>But euer within the Fraunchiſe they dwell</l>
               <l>and be but voyded from warde to warde.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <l>¶God helpe it is the more pitye,</l>
               <l>that ſuche folke be vncorrect:</l>
               <l>But yet I haue ſéene ſuch within this cittie</l>
               <l>openly puniſhed, and then abiect.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶Ye but not all the whole ſect,</l>
               <l>there be other that be much wurs:</l>
               <l>But yf they be any time detect:</l>
               <l>they be puniſhed by the Purs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <l>¶In hope to amend they haue that ſuffrance</l>
               <l>but I can perceaue there amends but few</l>
               <l>And vnder colour is their continuance,</l>
               <l>wold God I could their demeanours ſhew.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>That hope and fauour (mée think) is nought</l>
               <l>they ſhould if I might, no time borow:</l>
               <l>But with ſhame be openly foorth brought</l>
               <l>and for euer to be ouoyde with ſorow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:3"/>
               <speaker>The Auctour.</speaker>
               <l>¶I haue much wonder how they can finde,</l>
               <l>prouiſion ſtyll for to abide,</l>
               <l>And how they can get any friend,</l>
               <l>theyr noughty dooing ſo for to hide.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶They make good meales and geue gifts,</l>
               <l>haunte with the beſt where they dwell,</l>
               <l>From time to time, make harde ſhifts,</l>
               <l>cheriſh Officers and rewarde them well.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <l>¶By that ſaying they haue bolſterers</l>
               <l>to beare them out to their noughtyneſſe</l>
               <l>I beleue well, for where be receyuers:</l>
               <l>Theues may the better do their buſineſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶Alas (alas) the abhomination,</l>
               <l>ſtinketh afore the face of God:</l>
               <l>Doubtleſſe in many ſtrainge faſhion,</l>
               <l>he beateth with his violent rod.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour</speaker>
               <l>*No maruell it is, we be ſo vnkinde,</l>
               <l>lyke br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e beaſtes, diſordinate:</l>
               <l>As mad people, cleane out of minde,</l>
               <l>and that cauſeth God vs for to caſtygate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶Doth not the Mother leade the doughter,</l>
               <l>and be her Bawde too ſhamfully:</l>
               <l>The Brother alſo to his Siſter.</l>
               <l>and Siſter to Siſter, this is ſéene dayly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:4"/>
               <speaker>The Auctour.</speaker>
               <l>¶Yea, the Huſband to his owne wyfe,</l>
               <l>and caryeth her from place to place:</l>
               <l>The Father to his child vſeth this lyfe,</l>
               <l>alas héere is defaut of grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶In heads of Paryſhes is great blame,</l>
               <l>to ſuffre them in their company:</l>
               <l>But they care not of their name nor fame,</l>
               <l>Nor whence they come, make no inquiry,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <l>¶So they be gay what ſhall it néede?</l>
               <l>boaſtyng and faceing late and early:</l>
               <l>They he taken honeſt in word and déede,</l>
               <l>ſo they ſpend out with them largely.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>¶But yf a poore man lack of his duty,</l>
               <l>to the Church, houſe rent: or expence:</l>
               <l>Liue he neuer among them ſo honeſtly,</l>
               <l>Yet wil they be glad to haue them thence</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <l>¶Yea, and be arreſted or ſyted to the law</l>
               <l>outlawed, curſed or ſuſpended</l>
               <l>Diſdayned, puniſhed and kept in awe</l>
               <l>and the other by them euer defended.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Printer.</speaker>
               <l>*Thus money maketh the difference,</l>
               <l>the good to be nought, &amp; nought to be good,</l>
               <l>And in them both, is lyke reuerence:</l>
               <l>in money it lyeth, by all likelyhood.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:4"/>
               <speaker>The Authour.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶Then I ſée well there is ſmall charity,</l>
                  <l>and leſſe wiſdome in their circumſpect:</l>
                  <l>It hurteth their Neighbourall honeſty,</l>
                  <l>I can no more, but God it direct.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶Amen, God graunt it, for Chriſtes ſake,</l>
                  <l>to open the eyes of them in Auctority</l>
                  <l>To finde out theſe filthes: and ſuch order take</l>
                  <l>vtterly to wéede out the ſeede of iniquitye.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>*FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:5"/>
            <head>¶ The Authour to his Booke.</head>
            <l>GO lytle booke vnto my maſters al</l>
            <l>which haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of town or citie</l>
            <l>Deſire y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wardmote queſts in ſpecial</l>
            <l>And eke the Conſtables to ouer ſee:</l>
            <l>Theſe bawdi hoſtries ful of iniquity</l>
            <l>For better were it to haue a bordell</l>
            <l>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe place of the citie</l>
            <l>Than vnder their noſes ſo manifeſt to dwell.</l>
            <l>And ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt wonder inwardly,</l>
            <l>that honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer their preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
            <l>Or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their wyues to haunt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany</l>
            <l>And amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g neibors to kepe reſidence</l>
            <l>Seing by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch inconuenience</l>
            <l>For though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neighbours dare not,</l>
            <l>Reproue ſuch queanes openly:</l>
            <l>Yet deeme they ſuch of yll reports,</l>
            <l>As dayly kepe their company.</l>
            <trailer>¶ FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:5"/>
            <head>¶The diſcouery or blaſing of the <hi>common practiſes of beaſtly</hi> Bawdes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Wretched world waltring in wickednes</l>
               <l>Geuen all to miſchiefe and vnhappines:</l>
               <l>Vicious of liuing, barren of goodnes,</l>
               <l>with all vicyouſneſſe ſore infect:</l>
               <l>But one thing there is in ſpeciall,</l>
               <l>Which greueth mée ouer all:</l>
               <l>That bawdry is ſo vniuerſall:</l>
               <l>and ſo many there be of that ſect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>☞ Now a dayes, what is the cauſe &amp; why?</l>
               <l>Men haue their wiues in ſuch ielouſy:</l>
               <l>It is none other ſaue onely bawdry:</l>
               <l>through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which vicyous ſuffraunce</l>
               <l>Many yonge women as dayly we ſee:</l>
               <l>Breake Matrymony and alſo Virginitie,</l>
               <l>And all this commeth througe mother B.</l>
               <l>called a Bawde of the deuyls alyaunce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Through whoſe vngracious counſell,</l>
               <l>Much worſe then the Deuill of Hell</l>
               <l>Who ſo their tale to them doth tell:</l>
               <l>that many then make to them conſent</l>
               <l>Both wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Wolde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>But kept the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:6"/>
               <l>¶ For he that is diſpoſed viciouſly,</l>
               <l>Huntyng his appetyte to ſatiſfie</l>
               <l>In ſuch a place where that conueniently:</l>
               <l>Him ſelfe may not complayne.</l>
               <l>Then ſhall he a bawdy harlot get,</l>
               <l>And promiſe her a Skarfe of Sarcenet</l>
               <l>A Veluet Hat, or a Kyrtell of worſted</l>
               <l>His purpoſe to obtayne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Then goeth ſhe about full buſyly</l>
               <l>And handeleth her matter full craftely</l>
               <l>Fulfilled all with deuyllyſhe polycy:</l>
               <l>Of nothing ſtandeth ſhe in doubt,</l>
               <l>But tell her tale with ſpirit bolde,</l>
               <l>Lyke as a bawdy queane ſhould</l>
               <l>That neuer was good yong nor olde</l>
               <l>To bring her purpoſe about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Then wyll ſhe ſay to this woman quickly,</l>
               <l>Alas good Miſtreſſe, it is great pitie:</l>
               <l>I heare ſay ye liue not merely,</l>
               <l>Your Huſband to you is vnkynd,</l>
               <l>But if you wyll doo after mee?</l>
               <l>I warrant you and your honeſty:</l>
               <l>Ye ſhall neuer deſteyned be</l>
               <l>And alſo haue a dayly friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Alſo your Huſband is often abſent</l>
               <l>Wherwith youth is not content.</l>
               <l>And maketh the Woman often to repent,</l>
               <l>As many haue done ere this:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8639:6"/>Therfore youth deſireth the company</l>
               <l>Of them that be yong freſh and luſty:</l>
               <l>To paſſe away the time pleaſantly:</l>
               <l>Therfore take ye time, whan it is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶And one thyng I put you in aſſurance,</l>
               <l>There is a Gentleman of mine acqueintance</l>
               <l>whiche in you hath put his affiance,</l>
               <l>And loueth you with all his hart:</l>
               <l>Wherfore I beſeeche you hartely,</l>
               <l>Come one day and keepe hym company,</l>
               <l>And we wyll haue a chamber ſecretly,</l>
               <l>And at your pleaſure to departe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶And whan ſhe hath ſhowed her entent,</l>
               <l>And ſeeth the wyll not to her conſent:</l>
               <l>Then ſayeth ſhe to her incontinent:</l>
               <l>I wolde for no worldly treaſure:</l>
               <l>Doo or ſay that thing that ſhould ſownd</l>
               <l>To your diſhoneſtly for a thouſand pownd</l>
               <l>And yet more ouer I dare be bownd:</l>
               <l>It ſhall neuer be to your diſpleaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſome yong woman wil al Bawds dei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ye,</l>
               <l>And ſaith ſhe loueth not the company</l>
               <l>Of thoſe Harlots that vſe ſuch bawdry</l>
               <l>for many good women they ſpill:</l>
               <l>O good Miſtris, a Bawde not ſo,</l>
               <l>Saith this Bawde againe her vnto:</l>
               <l>It is one honeſt woman for another to doo:</l>
               <l>In ſuch caſe their pleaſure to fulfyl:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:7"/>
               <l>¶ For I know well, the courſe muſt be had</l>
               <l>Of this world: both with good and bad,</l>
               <l>And ſpecially, with ſuche as be lad</l>
               <l>In the Chaine of their flooryſhyng youth:</l>
               <l>Wherfore, good Maiſtreſſe, haue no dreede,</l>
               <l>For ye ſhall haue me as ſure in déede,</l>
               <l>As a truſtie friende at euery néede,</l>
               <l>I promys you for a trueth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Wyll ye not ſée this harlot bawdy?</l>
               <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w ſhe calleth all this honeſtie?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o entice a woman to lyue viciouſly,</l>
               <l>Is not this a pyteous caſe?</l>
               <l>But if ſhe ſhould haue her true hire,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nt ſhould ſhe bée in a hot fire,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eache all other how they deſire</l>
               <l>An honeſt woman to a bawdy place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Thus wyl this ſtrumpet, with faire words féede</l>
               <l>This good yong woman, whiche is in dréede,</l>
               <l>For to conſent to any ſuche deede,</l>
               <l>Were it not for ſuch Harlots inticement:</l>
               <l>Wherby ſhe is brought into this follie,</l>
               <l>Regardyng nothyng her owne honeſtie,</l>
               <l>But makes her a promys firme &amp; faithfully,</l>
               <l>To come to her at leaſure conuenient.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet wyl not this Bawd ieaue her babblyng</l>
               <l>Tyll ſhe haue got from her ſomthyng,</l>
               <l>Either her Bracelets, or els a Ryng,</l>
               <l>This wyll ſhe of her be ſure:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8639:7"/>Then ſhe goeth thence, as mery as a Pye,</l>
               <l>Home to her Hoſpytall of Bawdrie,</l>
               <l>And ſheweth the man all the matter plainly</l>
               <l>How ſhe hath brought her to lure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶But who be they that thoſe Bawdes bée?</l>
               <l>Be they the poore olde women (trow ye?)</l>
               <l>Nay, nay: they be of a hier degree,</l>
               <l>They be of the gorgeous ſort:</l>
               <l>They be thoſe that can them ſelfe paynt,</l>
               <l>No man by their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinance can the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attaint,</l>
               <l>For they looke as ſmooth as it were a Saint,</l>
               <l>Sad both of countenance and of porte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Yea (perhaps) ſhe weare a Hood of Veluet,</l>
               <l>A Kyrttell of Grograyne, or fine Worſtet,</l>
               <l>Of Satten, Damaſk, or Chamlet,</l>
               <l>Begarded &amp; fringed, as a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
               <l>That no man lyuyng, but he would truſt,</l>
               <l>His wyfe to go, where euer ſhe luſt,</l>
               <l>With this Strumpet falſe and vniuſt,</l>
               <l>In whome is no grace nor affiance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Wherby oftentimes, men are begylde,</l>
               <l>And their Wyues honeſtie cleane exylde,</l>
               <l>And many yong Maydens be get with childe</l>
               <l>through their ſubtyll vngracious counſell,</l>
               <l>But I would euery man would conſent,</l>
               <l>That they might haue condigne puniſhment</l>
               <l>For if their tongues were from their mouths rent</l>
               <l>yet were they ſerued but too well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:8"/>
               <l>¶ O ye Bawdes abhominable,</l>
               <l>Shameles wretches moſt miſerable:</l>
               <l>Amend your liues vituperable:</l>
               <l>But ſure I think ye be paſt remedy,</l>
               <l>Wherfore except ye doo amend</l>
               <l>I feare ye ſhall alow diſcend:</l>
               <l>With the Deuyll of hell to make your end.</l>
               <l>And there to raigne perpetually.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶The Deuyll in you hath taken ſuch place,</l>
               <l>That ye be paſt all ſhame and grace:</l>
               <l>So that ye may get money apace,</l>
               <l>Or els ſome other rewarde:</l>
               <l>Ye care not how many ye bryng to nought</l>
               <l>In euery corner, ye ſhall be ſought,</l>
               <l>For the Deuyl in you ſo déepe hath wrought</l>
               <l>That nothing God ye regarde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ O ye yong women in your youth luſty,</l>
               <l>Which haue taken vpon you matrymony</l>
               <l>Wherby ye be bound and that onely</l>
               <l>Your huſband all other aboue:</l>
               <l>To loue and pleaſe in ſpecyall</l>
               <l>And not to be vniuerſall,</l>
               <l>Nor haue affeccyon to any at all,</l>
               <l>But only him to loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Alſo beware ye yong Maydens, I ſay,</l>
               <l>Ye may ſe how that euery day</l>
               <l>Many take leaue and ren a way</l>
               <l>as great as they may wagge:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8639:8"/>Wandrynge abroade, al ouer the countrée,</l>
               <l>Compelled to ſteale or run away</l>
               <l>Or els to that, the beſt of thrée,</l>
               <l>To go with a Staffe and a Bagge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Wherfore, take héede, ye do not incline</l>
               <l>To any of theſe Bawdes, neither courſe nor fine</l>
               <l>In any wiſe folowe not their lyne</l>
               <l>But let them ſyt with yll reſt,</l>
               <l>Stop taſt your eares, heare not their tale,</l>
               <l>For if ye do: ye ſet on ſale</l>
               <l>Good name and honeſtie, for euer to fayle:</l>
               <l>Wherfore, truſt not to their falſe beheſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Their wordes be hony, their counſell is gall,</l>
               <l>A great ſtronge poyſon infernall,</l>
               <l>That poyſoneth body, ſoule and all,</l>
               <l>Suche is their operation:</l>
               <l>For, that which the Deuyll with all his power</l>
               <l>May not obtayne, (thoughe he conioure)</l>
               <l>They wyll bryng it to paſſe within an houre,</l>
               <l>With their ſwéete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶O ye men, the whiche maintayne,</l>
               <l>Suche bawdy queanes, thus for to raigne:</l>
               <l>Men ſaid I? nay that I lye playne:</l>
               <l>But vyle wretches abhomynable?</l>
               <l>Ye wyll not ſticke to ſpende quickly</l>
               <l>Twentie marke, to do your neighbour iniurie,</l>
               <l>But for Gods ſake, to ſpende an halfpeny,</l>
               <l>ye thynke it is right chargeable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:8639:9"/>
               <l>¶But what ſoeuer your Bawdes wyll craue,</l>
               <l>She néede but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, and ſhe ſhall haue</l>
               <l>Though other therfore, ye poll and ſhaue</l>
               <l>(Me thinkes) this thing, full yll doth frame:</l>
               <l>For body and gooddes, ye conſume in waſte,</l>
               <l>That the Deuyll, wyll haue ye all at the laſt,</l>
               <l>Without ye take t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, ere tyme be paſt,</l>
               <l>For to repent, and amende for ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶And if ye muſt néedes ſatiſfie,</l>
               <l>The Deuyllyſh appetite of your body</l>
               <l>Take a wyfe of your owne in Matrymonie,</l>
               <l>And none other man to beguyle.</l>
               <l>But ye regarde not what wretched lyfe,</l>
               <l>What ſhame and wo, what dayly ſtryfe,</l>
               <l>Ye make betwene the man and the wyfe,</l>
               <l>ſo ye obtayne your purpoſe vyle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶And ye that haue the Gift, to lyue chaſte,</l>
               <l>Looke ye ſpende not your gooddes in waſte,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſte God take vengeance of you in haſte,</l>
               <l>And withdrawe from you his grace:</l>
               <l>Reléeue the ſame, and the blinde that ye ſée,</l>
               <l>Beſtow well your talent, after your degrée,</l>
               <l>So that your liuing may not, a ſtumblyng Block bee</l>
               <l>To hinder other in this caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶But now for a concluſion finall</l>
               <l>Theſe Bawdes are the cauſe of miſchiefes all,</l>
               <l>That I pray God, foule might they fall,</l>
               <l>Except they ſhortly amende:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8639:9"/>For my minde is not able to expreſſe,</l>
               <l>Halfe their miſchiefe and vnhappineſſe</l>
               <l>That I beſeeche God of his goodneſſe,</l>
               <l>All vertuous people from them defende.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶O ye women that vertuous bée</l>
               <l>Ladyes and Gen yl women, of euery degrée,</l>
               <l>I pray you hartely to pardon mee,</l>
               <l>If I haue written, or ſaid amiſſe,</l>
               <l>But all my purpoſe is only</l>
               <l>Your worſhyp to ſaue and honeſtie,</l>
               <l>Wherfore I promys you faithfully,</l>
               <l>I haue not ſayd, but as it is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And if I haue in any condicion</l>
               <l>Spoken that, that diſpleaſeth any good perſon,</l>
               <l>I commyt mee to their correction,</l>
               <l>Beſeechyng God of his infinite grace:</l>
               <l>Wheras we haue lyued viciouſly,</l>
               <l>We may amende through his great mercy,</l>
               <l>And with him to reigne eternally,</l>
               <l>In his celeſtiall place.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>¶Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:10"/>
            <head>An Exclamacion of the Auctor, againſt the ſecrete Bawdes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Wicked traitors deceitful as deuils</l>
               <l>And wurs tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuils by very reaſon</l>
               <l>The Deuyll can neuer vtter his euylles</l>
               <l>In this caſe, but by your encheaſon:</l>
               <l>Promooters of Hell at euery ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>Proctors of Pluto, Attornets of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
               <l>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, the perfit ſoule of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt ſhameful brokers &amp; helpurueiours</l>
               <l>Porters of miſchiefe, drabbes damnable</l>
               <l>Enqueſtours of deth, of ſin Arbytrours,</l>
               <l>Odyble cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellours, of God reprouable:</l>
               <l>Marchants of miſery moſt deteſtable</l>
               <l>Sumners of ſorow, Hoſtlers infernall:</l>
               <l>The deuyl, deth &amp; bel, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are peregal.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Vnhappy earth how canſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſuſtayne,</l>
               <l>Theſe hell hounds fro thy profundytie?</l>
               <l>How art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> noriſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heuenly raine?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8639:10"/>Suffryng on thee, their great enormitie</l>
               <l>Why ſtandeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wals of Towne or citie?</l>
               <l>Compaſſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; doth not ouerthrow,</l>
               <l>Why doth any Foode, for them breede or grow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Margery Curſon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe of bawdes all</l>
               <l>Which at ſtewſyde, lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time kept reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>A bawde indeed, by right me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did her cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Yet by her cam not half thinco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>For al openly was done her inſolence:</l>
               <l>But of preui bawds, no perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bewar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>O curſed ſpirits, too ſhameful is your ſnare</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶O ribawd theues, how can ye procur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>To haue the fauour of honeſt liuing me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>How can your Ruffians life be ſure?</l>
               <l>To haunt the compani of honeſt wome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Your Apleſquiers, do daily trace &amp; ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Among fiſgigs. and bawdy knaues,</l>
               <l>Subiecting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in maner as your ſlaue</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Al maner ſtates w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in your trap is take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Your wri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g gins, ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly can be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>No fyſh, nor frogs, by you is forſaken.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8639:11"/>Goth one &amp; other falleth into your hand</l>
               <l>Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeruing ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wife &amp; huſband</l>
               <l>Wydow, Maide, Batcheler &amp; Prentice,</l>
               <l>With bawdy councel, ye do to lin entice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye mayntaine by your rotten bawdry,</l>
               <l>Vices of lechery and deteſtation,</l>
               <l>Inceſt, rape, ſacriledge and aduontery:</l>
               <l>Theft, murder, ſwearing: &amp; defloracion,</l>
               <l>Drunkenneſſe, picking, and defamacion</l>
               <l>Feightyng, brawling, hordome &amp; ſhame,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll theſe be Aſſiſtantes, to your bawdy name.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>¶ FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don, in the vpper end of Fleetlane: <hi>at the Signe of the ſpreade Eagle.</hi> by Richard Ihones.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8639:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
